# SHAZIA RUYBAL-PESÁNTEZ

Genomic Epidemiologist (PhD) | MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, Imperial College London

I am a genomic epidemiologist with expertise in population genetics, bioinformatics, and epidemiology of infectious diseases, particularly malaria. I am based at Imperial College London and am an Adjunct Associate Professor at Universidad San Francisco de Quito in Ecuador. For a list of my publications, see Google Scholar.



## QUALIFICATIONS

2018

The University of Melbourne

PhD in Genetic Epidemiology

Melbourne. Australia

2012

The Colorado College

BA in Biology

Oclorado Springs, CO, USA



## SELECTED RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2022 Present

# Research Associate, Dept of Infectious Disease Epidemiology

MRC GIDA, Imperial College London

- · Developing novel methods and computational tools to analyse genomic data to support malaria molecular surveillance. My projects include:
- simplegen R package to simulate malaria genetic epi to explore the "power" of genomic surveillance sampling designs
- C DRpower Shiny app (not yet public) to simplify the design of studies that monitor rapid diagnostic tests effectiveness for malaria diagnosis in the field
- & Skills used: R, RMarkdown, Github, Shiny, Quarto, Python

2021 2022

#### Visiting Scientist, Institute of Microbiology

Universidad San Francisco de Quito

Quito. Ecuador

- Support the coordination and data analysis (ongoing) of a cohort study to understand vaccine and infection-induced immunity to SARS-CoV-2
- · Support data analysis (ongoing) on the genomic epidemiology and phylogenetics of SARS-CoV-2 in Ecuador
- & Skills used: REDCap, R, RMarkdown, Github, HPC/SLURM

2020

#### **Consultant Epidemiologist**

#### Freelance

Quito, Ecuador

- · Consulted for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and Migration & National COVID-19 Emergency Response Committee providing internal analyses on case/testing trends and epi modelling (importation dynamics, Reff)
- · Consulted for the Ecuadorian Red Cross National Blood Bank to establish SARS-CoV-2 sero-surveillance as part of the COVID-19 emergency response, delivered a surveillance flexdashboard (not public)
- / Skills used: R, RMarkdown, Github, Dashboards

2019 2022

#### Research Associate, Population Health and Immunity Division

Walter & Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research

Melbourne, Australia

- Supported field implementation and lead the overall analysis (ongoing) of a 12month longitudinal cohort study in Papua New Guinea
- Work involved flexdashboard for routine updates and data viz of both operational logistics aspects and real-time epidemiological trends
- · Worked with large epidemiological datasets from a range of malaria, vectorborne diseases, and COVID-19 projects and led the data curation, management and analysis using reproducible workflows
- / Skills used: Applied epi, R, RMarkdown, Github/Gitlab, Dashboards, Shiny



## CONTACT INFO

s.ruybal@imperial.ac.uk

github.com/shaziaruybal

shaziaruybal.com

I am an experienced R user for data processing, vizualization, communication, reports/dashboards, shiny apps, workshop development/organization and am passionate about open science and the development of digital tools for research. See below for more details.

#### **SKILLS**

✓ Full experience in genetic/genomic sequencing data analysis, population genetic and epidemiological methods, database curation/management, and reproducible research workflows

Expert in R (tidyverse), RStudio, RMarkdown, Shiny, SLURM/HPC

Experienced in Git/Github, LaTeX, CSS, HTML, Quarto, Python, REDCap

#### LANGUAGES

(RStudio)

Native speaker English and Spanish French Level A2 Dutch Level A1

## ADDITIONAL TRAINING

2021: Short course: Multiple imputation in R (Victorian Centre for Biostatistics) 2021: Diversity Scholar Workshop

2018: Certification "Teaching Skills for Graduate Researchers (University of Melbourne)

2017: Winter School in Mathematical **Biology** (The University of Queensland) 2015: Short course: Spatial mapping and GIS R skills (University of Melbourne) 2014 2019

## PhD Researcher/Research Associate, Bio21 Institute

University of Melbourne

Melbourne, Australia

- Applied genomic epidemiology approaches (bioinformatic and population genetic methods) using R to better understand the malaria transmission dynamics in Ecuador and Ghana
- & Skills used: Applied epi, R, RMarkdown, Github, Data management/curation



## POSITIONS

2022-Present Research Associate, Imperial College London

2020-Present Adjunct Associate Professor, Universidad San Francisco de Quito

2019-Present Research Fellow (now Honorary), University of Melbourne, Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research

2019-2022

Honorary Research Fellow, Burnet Institute, Australian Centre for Research Excellence in Malaria Research and Centre for the Elimination of Neglected Tropical Diseases

2012-2014

Research Assistant, New York University School of Medicine



# SELECTED TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2019-2022 **R-Ladies Melbourne Inc** 

Registered female-led charity. >2300 members

Melbourne, Australia

 Leadership roles (Secretary, President) organising monthly meetups ranging from beginner to advanced R topics. See sidebar for workshops I have (co-)led

2019-Present

#### **Guest lecturer**

Ecuador/Australia

- 2019: Nossal Institute for Global Health MPH on Malaria and Child Health
- 2021: Universidad San Francisco de Quito MSc Innovation on COVID-19 epidemiology, variant dynamics and implications for public health in Ecuador

2016-Present

#### Student supervision

University of Melbourne

- Supervised/mentored students to completion in honors/undergrad (3), MSc (1) and PhD (3, 2 ongoing) with projects in population genetics, seroepidemiology, and computational biology. I serve on 3 PhD committees at UoM
- · Actively involved in the supervision, mentorship and capacity-building of researcher officers/technical staff in Papua New Guinea and Ecuador



# NOTABLE AWARDS

Apr 2021 **COVID-19 Digital Grant (Regional Collaborations Programme)** 

Australian Academy of Sciences & Dept of Industry, Science, Energy and Resources

Melbourne, Australia

• Awarded A\$10,000 as Chief Investigator for the collaborative project: Fit-forpurpose analytical tools to support COVID-19 sero-surveillance in Papua New Guinea. This led to the development of covidClassifyR

#### Dec 2019

## Kellaway Excellence Award in Education

Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research

Melbourne, Australia

 Awarded to recognize the significant contribution to improve female representation in statistical bioinformatics through joint leadership of R-Ladies Melbourne, the R programming community for women in Australia

## **DIGITAL TOOLS**

SIMPLEGEN: R package to simulate malaria genetic epidemiology

CovidClassifyR: Shiny app to process and analyse COVID-19 serological data. See my useR! 2022 presentation

CovidVaccinationScore: Shiny app to help individuals better understand their "priority" status during vaccine roll-out in **Ecuador** 

Ecuador blood bank COVID-19 serosurveillance flexdashboard (not opensource): presented

anonymized/aggregated SARS-COV-2 seroprevalence data from monthly screening of blood donation samples

ICEMR PNG weekly flexdashboard (not open-source): presented operational data (e.g. follow-up rates) for study team to plan field activities, as well as prelim epi trends (e.g. malaria test positivity)

## **WORKSHOPS**

Crea tu dashboard en R: Visualizando datos del mundial FIFA (Oct 2022): Presented at Brown Bag Seminar InnovaLab at Institute of Tropical Medicine/University Cayetano Heredia Peru (in Spanish) for the MSc program

**Applied Malaria Molecular Surveillance** workshop (Aug 2022): Co-organized 4day workshop for African researchers on how to use R-based data analysis tools for malaria genomics

Shiny app covidClassifyR workshop (March 2022): Led 4-day virtual workshop for researchers in Papua New Guinea on how to use covidClassifyR

Automate your CV in rmarkdown: easy as 1, 2, knit! (Feb 2022): Presented at R-Ladies Melbourne meetup, the recording has been viewed >5600 times

STEM Workshop "Solve an outbreak and become a disease detective" (Sep 2019 & 2022): Co-led workshop at "It Takes a Spark" Conference teaching young girls (Y7-12) epidemiology and R skills (materials)

Made with pagedown, source code

See more detailed CV here

Last updated on 2023-05-27